RITESH PATEL

Mobile: +91 9016 726 199 | Email: <u>riteshpatel5558@yahoo.com</u>

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/ritesh-patel-984a54118/

SUMMARY

Safety Officer with ten years of experience in the Chemical and construction industry, dealing with Industrial Safety,

Fire Prevention and Disaster Management.

Expertise in fire and safety inspections, Safety audit, preventive maintenance, providing training personnel on health &

safety aspects, developing, monitoring and evaluating occupational safety and health programs to ensure compliance

with international guidelines.

Strong ability to gather and investigate facts to determine causes of hazards, and devise corrective and preventive

measures for achieving desired goals.

Competent in documenting incident reports, material safety data sheets, and providing technical support in audits and

evaluation of safety standards.

Conversant with safety procedures to provide training on first-aid, fire prevention plans, handling hazardous materials

and different safety-related subjects.

• Well-developed communication & presentations skills to gather inputs from managers and workers for development

and delivery of training programs.

SKILL SET

Fire & Safety Inspections

Emergency Mock Drills

Disaster & Emergency Response Management

HSE Induction & Training

Hazard Identification and Risk Assessment

Safety audit

Hazid, hazop study, process safety management

EDUCATION

Post Graduate Diploma in Industrial Safety Management (PDIS) from Fire and Safety Forum, India, 2017

 Bachelor of Science (Fire & Safety) from College of Fire Technology, Ahmedabad, India (Affiliated to Gujarat University)2012

INDUSTRIAL TRAINING

• 21 days training and project on "Fire & Safety Systems" at Krishak Bharati Cooperative Limited (KRIBHCO), Surat, India

WORK EXPERIENCE

Organization	Designation	Duration
Shree hari construction, Ahmedabad, India	Fire and safety officer	March2021 – present
Bhagwati Industries, Ahmedabad, India	Safety Officer	July 2015 – February
		2021
Jay Chemical Industries Limited, Ahmedabad, India	Safety Officer	April 2014 – June 2015
Reliance Industries Limited, Dahej, India	Safety Supervisor	April 2013 – Feb 2014
Bhavani Industries, Ahmedabad, India	Fire & Safety Officer	April 2012 – March
		2013

KEY DELIVERABLES

- Conduct periodic inspections of firefighting equipment, fire alarm systems for preventive maintenance and repairs, apart from regular toolbox meetings
- Examine vehicles, electrical equipment including earth leakage circuit breakers, etc., for effective functioning
- Provide comprehensive training to fire and safety personnel on donning and doffing procedures
- Undertake emergency mock drills to prepare staff on evacuation procedures
- Prepare and maintain documentation of routine tasks, reports and certificates
- Execution and follow of legal compliances related to the fire and safety department